Welcome to another
Unnecessary Computer Things
Today we're going to try to
recreate the 10 PRINT Maze
in Jupiter ACE Forth
First we set up a pseudo
random number generator
These first few words /
functions are from the
Jupiter ACE Manual itself,
pages 82 through 84.
This first method, seedon,
gets the next random number
seed.
seed is a 16-bit integer
that jumps around enough
from our calculations to
look random.
the "@" symbol retrieves
the seed variable
then we manipulate it to
get a new value
finally we duplicate it
and "!" stores the value
back out to the variable.
Now that we have a seed value on
the top of the stack we can use that
in our rnd word.
We call the seedon word to get a new
value and then multiply that value
by a number 'n' that we placed on the
stack, to get a random number from
0 to n-1
I'm also going to include this rand
word that uses a slightly more
random value on a real Jupiter Ace
than the fixed seed we start with...
The location 15403 is the number of
frames displayed since power on,
and we'll initialize with that
value if 0 is on the stack before
the call.
This next word, gr, is on page 71 of
the manual, and allows you to
define an 8 by 8 character graphic
with 8 8-bit values on the stack
and the character code to assign
the mapping to.
11263 through 12287 store the patterns
for characters 0 through 127
8 bytes per character (1024 bytes
total)
c! (c-store) stores a single byte in an
address
We're actually starting at the end of
the memory slot for a character
because we're going to be putting the
values on the stack in order.
We're using i for the offset that
we're tracking in a do loop
and then doing a -1 at the end of the
iteration.
We end with a +loop, with is similar to
a branch if not equal instruction
in assembly that really just checks that
the loop variable is greater than 0.
Next, we define two characters using
base 2 (binary).
First, a backslash-like graphics
character. The text slashes don't
use all 8 lines, but only 4, so our
maze wouldn't have closed-in walls
if we used those.
We just put a 1 in for "on" pixels
and a 0 for "off" pixels.
Finally, we switch back to decimal
and call our "gr" word with "1" as
a character code.
Next, we reverse the order of the
pixels.
Now, we assign that to character 2.
Lastly, we write the maze word.
Clear the screen, loop 32 times 24
times (initialize loop counter to 0)
In the loop, emit a random number
and add 1.
Ok, so ERROR 2 is a buffer underflow.
What broke?
Well, the rnd word requires an "n"
value on the stack to set the random
range from 0 to n-1. Putting a 2 in
here will satisfy that requirement.
Now the maze should work!
Let's make that run a little longer
by adjusting that loop.
Oops... no colon before the edit
command.
Let's do 2 rows full of screens, or 48
lines.
This is definitely not a one-liner
maze, but a nice trade-off is that it
runs a lot closer to machine code,
because the words are compiled each
time. Also, a lot of the memory access
is stack-based (because it's Forth).
Ugh, who can type while being watched?
Thanks for watching!