Welcome to another
Unnecessary Computer Things
Today we're going to look at converting
the "Leapfrogs" game from the
last episode from Sinclair BASIC
to VIC-20 BASIC.
Starting out, I want to note that I
made an attempt to not change syntax if
it was legal and the logic worked for
the new platform.
I will slightly deviate from this
when I tweak the "game end" logic.
Let's start out by running the
original ZX80 program.
We immediately get a syntax error in
line 300 because Commodore VIC-20 BASIC
doesn't have an explicit screen clear
statement.
But we can substitute printing the "Clear"
character represented in quotes by this
reverse heart.
Next we need to choose printable
characters for the "leapfrogs"
initialized to the PETSCII values of a
heart and a spade instead of a reverse
quote and reverse space.
On line 360, we're printing out
numbers, but in Commodore BASIC,
numbers are padded with a character up
front for a possible minus sign and in
back to avoid the number running into
characters immediately after it.
We can substitute in the PETSCII value
for "0", 48, and add the digit we wish
to print to get a single character and
then pad a space manually.
Notice now that we're a character short
above the "5".
That's because P(5) is 0, which is
non-printable. Let's change that to the
PETSCII value for a space, 32.
On the ZX80, there are 32 characters
across. The VIC-20 only has 23, so
there's not enough space for
"ENTER MOVE".
Let's add a print on a line 490
before it.
Ok, now we can try our first move.
On the ZX80 "45" moves the 4 piece to 5.
On the VIC-20, we immediately get a
repeat to the input question mark,
indicating that our input was rejected.
Why?
Let's look at line 530.
Our input of "45" would mean that
F ("from") would be 4.5.
VIC-20 BASIC will return a float for 45
divided by 10 vs. 4 for ZX80 BASIC.
Let's force the result to an integer.
While we're at it let's look at the
rest of the move logic.
Lines 550 and 580 are looking for a 0,
but our empty slot value is now 32.
So we need to check for equal to 32
instead of equal to 0 on line 550
and greater than 32 in our T ("to") slot
instead of 0 (not equal would work as
well) on line 580.
Also, the P(F) space left behind needs
to be 32 now.
Now we need to check the "end game"
logic.
In the original program, "X" is being
used to track if there are any
conditions to continue the game.
We can remove this since line 750 is
also depending on a value of 0 for
the empty slot as a shortcut.
We'll look for a space in P(5) on
line 760
And we need to rewrite the logic a bit
for line 730.
For ZX80, the logic is relying both on
the two leapfrog characters
being 128 and 129 and boolean true
returning -1.
That works for Commodore BASIC to some
degree, but we need to do more math,
so I'm opting for boolean AND and OR on
line 730 and looking for the heart and
spade values in their original slots as
a sign to continue the game.
Lastly, there is no "code" keyword in
VIC-20 BASIC, but we can check that
the leftmost character is a "y" instead.
And finally, we can run the game.
Thanks for watching! Please comment with any
ideas and like and subscribe!